Okay, so today's דף daf is דף ל"א, Daf Lamed Alef, and
we pick up on two-thirds down on the דף, daf, the beginning
of the new
פרק. Perek. מי שקנא לאשתו ונסתרה, Mishe kinu le-ishto ve-nistara, a man
warned his wife not to go to seclusion and she went into
seclusion. This brings us back to the very opening משנה Mishna of
the מסכת. Masechet. אפילו שמע מעוף פורח יוציא ויתן כתובה דברי רבי
אליעזר. Afilu shama mi-of poreach yotzi ve-yiten ketubah divrei Rabbi Eliezer. So
how many witnesses, what proof do you need that she went into
seclusion to be able to continue the סוטה Sotah process? So if
you remember רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer in the opening משנה Mishna had
said even one witness, even the husband, and here the גמרא, Gemara,
the משנה Mishna states it even more radically, even if like a
passing bird claimed it. No matter what the type of a claim
was, if there's somebody claiming that she went into seclusion, that is
enough basis to make her drink the סוטה Sotah water. Seems extremely
unfair for her. That is the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
So יוציא ויתן כתובה yotzi ve-yiten ketubah means he now is obligated
to make her drink the סוטה Sotah water, or you know, she
is now forbidden to him as a סוטה, Sotah, and if they
don't want to go through the process of the סוטה Sotah water,
he must divorce her and give the כתובה ketubah if he doesn't
want to make her go through the process. So it's a little
bit of funny, it should have said that he should make her
drink, why does it say he should give her the כתובה, ketubah,
why doesn't it say if she refuses then she goes out without
a כתובה? ketubah? But anyway, this is the way רש"י Rashi is
understanding it, that it means that she's obligated to drink the water
or she's forbidden to him and therefore either she drinks the water,
if he refuses, she gets divorced without a כתובה, ketubah, if he
doesn't want to go through the process, he divorces her and gives
the כתובה. ketubah. Now רבי יהושע אומר עד שיהיו נושאות ונותנות בה
נשים במטויה בלבנה. Rabbi Yehoshua omer ad she-ye-hayu venot ba-mazos balevana. He
says, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, no, it's not a problem until
the women who sort of knit by the moonlight, until they start
like gabbing about her and gossiping about her. Now what does that
mean? רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua normally says that you need two witnesses
that she went into seclusion to make her drink. So actually what
it's saying here is not a הלכה halacha about that she is
considered forbidden to her husband. There's no witnesses she went into seclusion,
but you have these rumors about her. Once there are rumors about
her, based on the פסוק pasuk of טהורה היא, tehora hee, that
she is pure, well here her reputation has already been sullied, so
the waters won't work. Okay, so the waters won't work, that's not
an option anyway. There has not been witnesses that she was in
seclusion,
so really what are the options? Well, in this case where there
are no witnesses, he really could stay married to her, there's just
this bad reputation about her, but she's not forbidden as a סוטה.
Sotah. But if he doesn't want to stay married to her because
of this reputation, then he would divorce her and he would pay
the כתובה. ketubah. So it's actually quite a bizarre read, you know,
in רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer case, the יוציא ויתן כתובה yotzi ve-yiten
ketubah means she is טמאה temeah and she can be forced to
drink the סוטה Sotah water, and in the רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
she's not טמאה temeah and it's just saying if he wants to
divorce her at this stage, he should pay the כתובה. ketubah. So
it's a really hard read, but this is the way רש"י Rashi
reads the משנה. Mishna. Now, now we get to the believability of
the one witness after seclusion. So there are two witnesses, let's say
that she secluded according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, and you might
remember that the הלכה halacha is that the תורה Torah would believe
once you have the basis that she was warned and she was
in seclusion, that if one witness would come and testify and say
that he saw her commit adultery within this seclusion, that would have
believe, not God forbid to put her to death, but to basically
say she can't drink the סוטה Sotah water, she's been a proven
adulteress and gets divorced without the כתובה. ketubah. So now we are
going to look at the parameters about this עד אחד eid echad
when he is believed. So let's take a look. עד אחד אומר
אני ראיתי שנטמאה, Eid echad omer ani raiti she-nitme'ah, if one witness
said 'I saw her that she became טמאה, temeah, that she committed
adultery in this seclusion,' לא הייתה שותה, lo hayeta shota, she would
not drink. ולא עוד אלא אפילו עבד אפילו שפחה הרי אלו נאמנים
אפילו פוסלה מכתובתה. Velo od ela afilu eved afilu shifcha harei elu
ne'emanim afilu foslah miketubatah. This idea that once there were two witnesses
of seclusion, one witness then builds on that to say that is
believed she says she became... committed adultery and she would no longer
be able to drink. So that one witness does not have to
be a kosher witness, even a slave, even a male or female
slave would be believed to invalidate her from the כתובה, ketubah, meaning
what are the consequences? If she's a proven adulteress, well you're not,
again, there's not two witnesses, you're not going to execute her, but
it means she can't drink the סוטה Sotah water, she has to
get divorced and she does not get her כתובה. ketubah. Now חמותה
ובת חמותה וצרתה ויבמתה ובת בעלה. chamota u-vat chamota ve-tzarata vi-yevimta u-vat
ba'ala. These are five women who are considered to be jealous of
the wife. Who are they? The mother-in-law, the sister-in-law, the mother-in-law's daughter,
the co-wife if the husband is married to two women,
the husband's dead brother's wife which the husband will have to do
יבום yibum on, so she's also not thrilled that there's another wife
in the picture, and her husband's daughter, step-daughter. All these people, we
can presume or we might want to under normal circumstances think that
they have some grudge against her. So what's the... So what's the
story, are they believed to say that she committed adultery?
So הרי אלו נאמנות, Harei elu ne'emanos, yes they are believed, ולא
לפוסלה מכתובתה אלא שלא תשתה. v'lo l'foslah miksubasah ella shelo tishseh. Now
because here we are concerned about you know their about about that
they might have some grudge or some something motivating it they we
you know we're concerned a little about their believability. In this case
they don't make her lose her כתובה. ketubah. It's enough she's a
proven adulteress that she can't won't go through with the סוטה sotah
drinking water, you know that there there's seen to be now enough
basis that we're not going to risk that whole process, but now
the husband has to divorce her and she takes her כתובה. ketubah.
So in this case okay she doesn't have an option of staying
married but she's actually going to get her כתובה. ketubah. Okay now
the משנה mishna continues: שהיה בדין. Shehayah vadin. Now how do we
know that this idea that an עד אחד ed echad is believed
to build on the idea of seclusion? Because this was something that
you could have learned out logically, meaning a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה עדות הראשונה שאינה אוסרתה איסור עולם אינה מתקיימת בפחות משנים, Umah
edus harishonah she'einah osartah issur olam einah miskayemes befachas mishnayim, I could
have made a קל וחומר kal vachomer that it wouldn't work. The
first testimony that she went into seclusion, seclusion is not locking her
sealing her fate because even after seclusion there's the test of the
סוטה sotah waters, and nevertheless even though it's not sealing her fate
the תורה Torah demanded that there be two witnesses. So if that's
true about the first testimony around the seclusion,
so עדות אחרונה שאוסרתה איסור עולם, Edus acharonah she'osartah issur olam, so
the second testimony that actually does make her forbidden for forever because
once there's witnesses that she one witness that she committed adultery she
could no you know that was it there was no way to
reverse that status, no drinking of the סוטה sotah water after that.
So in that case אינו דין שלא תתקיים בפחות משנים? Eino din
shelo siskayem befachas mishnayim? Before we seal her fate shouldn't we certainly
require two? So logically if I had not had a פסוק pasuk
I would have said that this one witness would not be believed
to seal her fate. תלמוד לומר ועד אין בה. Talmud lomar v'ed
ein bah. So it says that there is no witness against her
and she was not you know and she was not raped,
and meaning that if there is a witness against her there's a
problem. So the גמרא Gemara says כל עדות שיש בה. Kol edus
sheyesh bah. So there the way the גמרא Gemara is going to
interpret this is the way the משנה mishna sounds like it's saying
is עד ed even means one witness. Even one witness even something
very flimsy you know because that's we don't have one witness against
her you have to go through the you can go through the
process but if there was even one witness against her you wouldn't
have the process and her then it would be determined that she
has to get divorced. The גמרא's Gemara going to read it a
little slightly differently: there are not two witnesses against her there's only
one etc. We'll see that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. קל וחומר לעדות הראשונה מעתה. Kal vachomer l'edus
harishonah me'atah. Okay so now you've proven from this פסוק pasuk ועד
אין בה v'ed ein bah that if there's one witness against her
that she committed adultery her fate is sealed she gets divorced without
a כתובה. ketubah. Now let's use the קל וחומר kal vachomer to
go back and say that therefore the testimony of the seclusion one
should suffice. If you can seal her fate with one then shouldn't
the testimony of the seclusion which still has the סוטה sotah testing
be able to be done with one? ומה אם עדות אחרונה שאוסרתה
איסור עולם, Umah im edus acharonah she'osartah issur olam, the second testimony
of adultery that seals her fate הרי היא מתקיימת בעד אחד Harei
hi miskayemes b'ed echad is only one witness, עדות הראשונה שאינה אוסרתה
איסור עולם, Edus harishonah she'einah osartah issur olam, the testimony of seclusion
that doesn't seal her fate there's still the סוטה sotah water after
it, אינו דין שתתקיים בעד אחד? Eino din shesiskayem b'ed echad? Isn't
it logical that if that that one witness should be enough? You
know that's even a weaker status. So תלמוד לומר כי מצא בה
ערות דבר. Talmud lomar ki matza bah ervas davar. No because it
says in the case by a גט get interestingly not in the
case by a סוטה sotah that the husband found a matter of
you know nakedness of sexual
transgression regarding her. ולהלן הוא אומר על פי שנים עדים יקום דבר.
Ulehalan hu omer al pi shenayim eidim yakum davar. And when it
says the word דבר davar we know that that normally means by
two witnesses. So that's teaching you that מה להלן על פי שנים
אף כאן על פי שנים.
Mah lehalan al pi shenayim af kan al pi
shenayim. So the same way you know so so we see that
the normal testimony needs two and the testimony of מצא בה ערות
דבר matza bah ervas davar some matter of nakedness requires two. Now
that's a little funny because that sounds like the actual act itself.
The משנה mishna seems to be reading this that that's saying there's
some problem right the husband is divorcing his wife because of some
suspicion there's nothing in that פסוק pasuk about a גט get that
says she definitely committed it. So it's reading that in the context
of he suspects her and there were two witnesses for the seclusion.
The גמרא Gemara will play with it and read it in a
slightly different way. So we have the idea that you know and
again this is something the גמרא Gemara said this earlier that
there is a logic here. You need the two witnesses of seclusion
to create the reason for a suspicion and building on that reason
of suspicion the one witness is believed right so the reverse right
of one witness for seclusion would not be enough of a basis
to make her drink
the
סוטה sotah water. Or she does not collect her כתובה. Ketubah. It
is assumed that she did commit adultery. Okay. Now, עד אחד אומר
נטמאת ועד אחד אומר לא נטמאת. Ed echad omer nitme'is v'ed echad
omer lo nitme'is. Now what happens if you have competing testimonies? One
witness says she committed adultery, one says she did not. Now רש"י
Rashi points out that when the one witness says she did not,
it does not mean "I was looking into that room that she
was in seclusion and I saw that they didn't do anything wrong"
because as we'll see as the משנה Mishnah continues, you know, then
that would... well, we'll see why, but in a minute. But רש"י
Rashi says what it means is, he says "No, I know you
didn't see that because like you were with me or I was
with you there and I saw that you weren't seeing, you know,
that you weren't really looking in the room." Okay, so they're contradicting
one another. אשה אומרת נטמאת ואשה אומרת לא נטמאת, Ishah omeret nitme'is
v'ishah omeret lo nitme'is, or let's say it's not a person who's
normally a witness but it's a woman who normally would not count
as a witness and they're competing against each other. היתה שותה. Hayetah
shota. So she would drink. They would neutralize one another and she
would drink. Now because... so meaning so that it's like there was
no testimony at all. We do have the testimony that she went
into seclusion, so that's the basis of making her drink. So this
is why רש"י Rashi says that the witness that said לא נטמאת
lo nitme'is is not actually saying that "I saw her not commit
adultery" because if that's true and in a minute we're going to
have a case where two witnesses say that, so we would not
be talking about having her not drink. It's just לא נטמאת lo
nitme'is means that "I am saying, you know, what you're saying is
not correct" but not that I have active knowledge that she did
not commit adultery. Okay, so this משנה Mishnah makes it sound that
whether you say she did or she didn't, they have equal weight.
We'll see in the גמרא Gemara a very different approach. Okay. Now,
so... okay. אחד אומר נטמאת ושנים אומרים לא נטמאת. Echad omer nitme'is
u'shnayim omrim lo nitme'is. One said she became טמא Tamei and two
said she did not. היתה שותה. Hayetah shota. So again they sort
of neutralize one another, you go back to where you were and
you have the testimony of seclusion, so you can make her drink.
Because the one who said she became טמא Tamei is neutralized... if
even one witness can neutralize him then two can certainly neutralize him.
And here is really why רש"י Rashi has to say לא נטמאת
lo nitme'is means that they're not actively saying she didn't do it
because if two witnesses are actively saying she didn't, she obviously would
not drink. But they're neutralizing the one witness. Okay, now, שנים אומרים
נטמאת ואחד אומר לא נטמאת. Shnayim omrim nitme'is v'echad omer lo nitme'is.
So two say that she did commit adultery and one says that
she did not. לא היתה שותה. Lo hayetah shota. She would not
drink. Now that seems quite obvious and also if two witnesses said
it, why aren't we executing her? So we'll see in the גמרא
Gemara maybe they were not kosher witnesses. But anyway, the end of
the משנה Mishnah seems pretty obvious because it's basically the exact same
מהלך mahalach as if it was one and one as if it
was two and one. But we will take a look at... well
no, in the case of two and one in the last case
where the two are saying... I'm sorry, in the case where one
said she became טמא Tamei and two said she did not become
טמא, Tamei, that's the same as one and one. In the case
of the last case here, where you know she would drink, it
would neutralize. In the last case here where it says that two
said that she did become and one said she did not, that
you wouldn't let her drink. Okay, that's different than two and one
because there they don't neutralize, you go by the concern that she
did... that she did become טמא, Tamei, but it should seem relatively
obvious. So the גמרא Gemara will try to figure out what the
point is of this last part of the משנה, Mishnah, the two
and one parts of the משנה. Mishnah. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. האי תלמוד לומר כי מצא בה ערות דבר. Hai
talmud lomar ki matza bah ervat davar. So the גמרא Gemara jumps
to the part of the משנה Mishnah where it says: "How do
we know that the seclusion needs two?" If we're saying that the
testimony of actual adultery is one witness is sufficient, how do we
know that the seclusion needs two? And it quotes this פסוק pasuk
of by a גט Get that he found in her a matter
of nakedness. So the גמרא Gemara says why are we learning it
from that פסוק? pasuk? תלמוד לומר בה, בה ולא בקינוי בה ולא
בסתירה מיבעיא ליה. Talmud lomar bah, bah v'lo b'kinuy bah v'lo b'stirah
mibaya lei. There's a much more simple way of learning it out.
The פסוק pasuk that says that one witness is believed, עד אין
בה, ed ein bah, is when it's talking about the actual act
of adultery. So it says בה, bah, in regarding her, this is
when we say עד, ed, that one witness is enough, that's when
we're talking about the actual act of adultery. For other things, this
one witness isn't enough. For קינוי kinuy and סתירה stirah it's a
different discussion. So that's the דרשה drasha that the גמרא Gemara likes,
not the דרשה drasha in the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
הכי נמי קאמר. hachi nami ka'amar. Yes, let's... that is what the
משנה Mishnah says. It tries to read the משנה Mishnah according to
the way it understands. תלמוד לומר בה, בה ולא בקינוי בה ולא
בסתירה. Talmud lomar bah, bah v'lo b'kinuy bah v'lo b'stirah. Yes, how
do we know that you need two earlier? Because what the basis
of one has the word בה bah and that's limiting, so the
earlier stages you would actually need two or at least one of
those earlier stages.
וטומאה בעלמא בלא קינוי בלא סתירה דלא מהימנא. V'tumah b'alma b'lo kinuy
b'lo stirah d'lo mehemnat. Now, how do you know, once we've told
you that one witness is believed that she committed adultery when it's
building on the seclusion, maybe I would have a basis to say
that one witness would always be believed even when it's not building
on the seclusion? One witness says she committed adultery, the husband would
divorce her without a כתובה. ketubah. How do we know the general
principle that when it's not in this particular structure of the seclusion
and then the witness, that you actually need two witnesses and not
one? So how do we know that? נאמר כאן דבר ונאמר להלן
דבר מה להלן בשני עדים אף כאן בשני עדים. Ne'emar kan davar
ve'ne'emar lehalan davar ma halan bishnei eidim af kan bishnei eidim. Now,
because here it says, you know, דבר מצא בה ערות דבר davar
matza bah ervat davar and that means two witnesses, so that shows
you that when it's talking about normally about adultery you need two.
And that makes sense that the פסוק pasuk מצא בה ערות דבר
matza bah ervat davar is not about the seclusion, it's about a
basis, you know, that he really thinks she committed adultery. So that's
telling you the basis הלכה halakha that normal testimony about that needs
two, but when it's building on the testimony of seclusion, one suffices.
Okay. Now, עד אחד אומר נטמאת. eid echad omer nitmeit. Now we
are going to deal with the interesting part of the משנה, Mishnah,
you know, going beyond the דרשות, drashot, and about the one against
one where the משנה Mishnah makes it sound like they neutralize one
another. All right. And the גמרא Gemara is, we'll see, not going
to really adopt that position. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
טעמא דכמכחיש לה הא דמכחיש לה. Ta'ama dekhamachish leh ha demachish leh.
So the reason that, you know, it's neutralized is because it's one
against one. הא לא כמכחיש לה עד אחד מהימן. Ha lo kamachish
lei eid echad meheman. So first let's figure out about the basic
principle. Could have jumped to the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, but
it's building up to the one against one. How do we know
that one witness is believed? We saw that in the משנה Mishnah
but the גמרא Gemara is now going to spell it out.
Okay.
מנני מילי, Minani mili, where do you know this from? דתנו רבנן
ועד אין בה בשנים הכתוב מדבר. Detanu rabbanan ve'eid ein bah bishnayim
hakatuv medaber. There are no two witnesses against her. There are no
witness against her. Now again, it sounds like the משנה Mishnah saying
there's no one witness against her, you can go through the סוטה
sotah process; one witness you can't, you believe the one witness. The
גמרא Gemara does not read it that way. The גמרא Gemara says
there's no witness against her, the word witness means two witnesses.
בשנים הכתוב מדבר אתה אומר בשנים או אינו אלא באחד תלמוד לומר
לא יקום עד אחד באיש לכל עון ולכל חטאת. Bishnayim hakatuv medaber
atah omer bishnayim o eino ela be'echad talmud lomar lo yakum eid
echad be'ish lechol avon ulechol chatat. One witness cannot rise up against
a person. ממשמע שנאמר לא יקום עד איני יודע שהוא אחד? Mimachmashne'emar
lo yakum eid eini yode'a shehu echad? Why did you have to
say one single witness? Just say עד, eid, עד eid is in
the singular, it's not עדים. eidim. So I would have known that
עד eid means a single one. Okay.
מה תלמוד לומר אחד זה בני אב? Mah talmud lomar echad zeh
bnei av? This is like a principle, this is like
a model to learn from that: כל מקום שנאמר עד הרי כאן
שנים עד שיפרט לך הכתוב אחד. Kol makom she'ne'emar eid harei kan
shnayim ad sheyafrit lecha hakatuv echad. That the normal word עד eid
means two and it needs the qualifier of אחד echad to say
it means only one witness. So this is a general principle in
the גמרא Gemara in many, many cases when it deals with עדות
eidut that the word עד eid by itself means two witnesses. Okay.
But if it means two witnesses, how are they going to read
the פסוק? pasuk? The משנה Mishnah we understand how it read the
פסוק. pasuk. How is the גמרא Gemara going to read the פסוק?
pasuk? Okay. ואמר רחמנא, Ve'amar rachmana, so here's how it's going to
read it. ואמר רחמנא תרי לית בה אלא חד. Ve'amar rachmana trei
leit bah ela chad. So there's no two witnesses against her, there's
only one witness against her. והיא לא נתפשה אסורה. Ve'hi lo nitpasa
asura. So as opposed to saying, you know, ועד אין בה, ve'eid
ein bah, there's no witnesses against her, then she's going to go
through the process, it says no: there's no two witnesses against her,
there's only one witness against her and she wasn't raped. So then,
not stated in the פסוק, pasuk, then she'd be forbidden and you
would stop the process. Okay, then she'd be considered like she had
committed it and you would stop the process.
How exactly it reads that in the פסוק pasuk not so clear,
but that's how it's reading it. Okay.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: וכיון דמדאורייתא עד אחד
מהימן, Vekeivan demidraisa eid echad meheman, now we're getting to the point
we were about the משנה, Mishnah, the new part, not the דרשה,
drashah, that the one against one neutralizes. Since according to the תורה
Torah one witness is believed, אידך היכי מצי מכחיש לה? idach heichi
matzi machish leh? So that witness that says she committed adultery, that
witness is like a super-charged witness because he's coming with the suspicion
and with the
רגלים לדבר, raglayim ladavar, the foundation of the fact that she was
warned and she went into private and to seclusion, and the תורה
Torah says we're going to give particular strength to that person's testimony.
So how does a one person who's contradicting, that's just the normal
one witness. So the גמרא Gemara says that shouldn't have any weight.
Okay. אידך
היכי מצי מכחיש לה? Idach heichi matzi machish leh? The first one
was given special believability by the תורה. Torah. How does the other
one who says she didn't commit adultery, where does he get the
power to contradict? מכחיש לה? Machish leh? ואמר עולא עולא תני כל
מקום שמן התורה עד אחד הרי כאן שנים, Ve'amar Ulla Ulla tanni
kol makom sheminaTorah eid echad harei kan shnayim, wherever the תורה Torah
believes in an עד אחד, eid echad, which is here and a
few other cases, gave it special believability, הרי כאן שנים. harei kan
shnayim. That counts effectively as two witnesses. ואין דברו של אחד במקום
שנים. Ve'ein dvaro shel echad bemakom shnayim. And somebody that's normally an
עד אחד, eid echad, you know, it doesn't have this special believability,
that has no weight against this עד אחד eid echad that the
תורה Torah is treating as שנים. shnayim. like two witnesses. Okay, so
how here can it say that it's one against one? It goes
against עולא's Ulla statement and עולא's Ulla statement is a very logical
one based on the special believability of this one witness.
Okay, אלא
אמר עולא, ela amar Ulla, so rather עולא Ulla said, so they
had quoted עולא Ulla before and now
they're quoting עולא Ulla as
how he read the משנה. Mishna. תני לא היתה שוטה. tani lo
haitah shota. He actually had a different גרסא girsah of the משנה.
Mishna. Whether he had a different גרסא, girsah, he changed the גרסא,
girsah, but all the whole משנה Mishna that said one against one,
man against man, woman against woman, whatever, it all neutralizes and you
go back to the beginning and she would drink. עולא Ulla said
not that way, that the whole משנה Mishna was saying the exact
opposite, that if you have one witness saying that she became טמאה,
tameiah, then even if you have an equal one contradicting, the contradiction
is nothing and you would believe the one that she became טמאה,
tameiah, you would assume she committed adultery and you would not go
through with the process. Okay, so the משנה Mishna sounds like they
neutralize and you're back to where you started and עולא Ulla says
no, they don't neutralize, the contradicting witness is worthless and she's considered
to be טמאה. tameiah. Okay, לא היתה שוטה. lo haitah shota. וכן
אמר רבי יצחק לא היתה שוטה. v'chen amar Rabbi Yitzchak lo haitah
shota. And he also followed this approach and read the משנה Mishna
differently. So now the גמרא Gemara says ורבי חייא אמר היתה שוטה.
v'Rabbi Chiya amar haitah shota. But רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya kept the
משנה Mishna the way it was. No, she would drink. The one
against one would, you know, she'd be able to drink. You could
go forward. The one against one would neutralize. So now the גמרא
Gemara says לרבי חייא קשיא דעולא. l'Rabbi Chiya kashya d'Ulla. How about
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, isn't that, isn't עולא's Ulla statement a difficulty?
Now maybe you could say רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya didn't agree with
עולא, Ulla, but the way רש"י Rashi explains it, so רש"י Rashi
says it's not just that עולא Ulla said it, it's the sort
of power, the logical power in עולא's Ulla statement. If the תורה
Torah is giving believability to this witness especially because it's building on
the testimony of seclusion, then what logic does this statement mean that
the other witness can neutralize? So the גמרא Gemara says לרבי חייא
קשיא דעולא לא קשיא כאן בבת אחת כאן בזה אחר זה. l'Rabbi
Chiya kashya d'Ulla, lo kashya, kan b'vas achas, kan b'zeh achar zeh.
It depends whether the witnesses are coming at the same time or
one after the other. Now רש"י Rashi says at the same time
is an extreme definition of at the same time, they came like
תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur they testified. Whether you need exactly
that is not clear, but the logic of this distinction is clear,
which is that if they're coming at the same time, you know,
you didn't yet give weight to the first witness. Two people showed
up and they said we have what to say, and one person
says I saw her become טמאה tameiah and the other says no
you didn't. So in that case, like, you know, we have, we
just have a contradiction and we haven't given weight yet to the
testimony of the one who said she became טמאה tameiah because we
know there's another person here that has a different claim to say.
I think even whether, you know, it doesn't have to be בבת
אחת, b'vas achas, רש"י Rashi says בבת אחת. b'vas achas. But if
the first one witness came and said she became טמאה tameiah and
we gave it a weight and we recognized that testimony and then
the court, you know, sort of saw that, okay, she's established as
being טמאה, tameiah, then the testimony of what comes afterwards, you know,
does not, does not have weight. So that's the distinction. Now you
could have said, you know, maybe even if they came at the
same time, the first one has the seclusion to back it up.
But you do understand that when something is coming and it's being
challenged from the get-go, it does not exactly carry the same weight.
So that's the distinction, okay. So when the משנה Mishna says they
neutralize, it's when they came at the same time. Okay,
תנן, t'nan, now let's look at the final case of the משנה,
Mishna, the one against two. עד אומר נטמאת ושנים אומרים לא נטמאת
היתה שוטה. ed omer nitme'is v'shnayim omrim lo nitme'is, haitah shota. One
says she became טמאה tameiah and two said not, then that would
neutralize and you would continue with the process. Okay, הא חד וחד
לא היתה שוטה. ha chad v'chad lo haitah shota. So the גמרא
Gemara says now that's funny, it says if two says she didn't,
they would neutralize and you'd go forward with the process. Now the
משנה Mishna had just said one against one would neutralize. This says
no, two neutralizes the one, makes it sound that one wouldn't neutralize
the one. Well that works the way עולא Ulla reread the משנה.
Mishna. עולא Ulla read one against one, you would stop the process.
So then this line of the משנה Mishna says ah, but one
against two, that would neutralize and you would continue. But according to
רבי חייא תיובתא דרבי חייא, tyuvta d'Rabbi Chiya, according to רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya that doesn't make sense. What do you mean if two
came they would neutralize? Even if one would come he would neutralize,
assuming that again that we are talking that it all came at
the same time.
So you might be thinking that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya could explain
that the משנה Mishna that says one against two is when the
two came later, but okay, רש"י Rashi discusses that. But assuming it's
all talking at the same time, why did you have to say
one against two neutralizes if one against one neutralizes? So the
גמרא Gemara says תיובתא דרבי חייא, tyuvta d'Rabbi Chiya, אמר לך רבי
חייא ולטעמיך אימא סיפא. amar lach Rabbi Chiya u'ltameich eima seifa. No,
no, no, don't overread that the two against one suggests that one
against one would be different. Look, I'll prove it to you, just
look at the last case of the משנה. Mishna. שנים אומרים נטמאת
ואחד אומר לא נטמאת, shnayim omrim nitme'is v'echad omer lo nitme'is, two...
Who say she became טמאה tamei and one said that she did
not. לא הייתה שותה. Lo haysah shotah. So then that would stop
the process you would assume that she became טמאה, tamei, okay,
לא הייתה שותה. lo haysah shotah. החד וחד הייתה שותה? Ha-chad ve-chad
haysah shotah? So would you say that if it was one and
one she would drink?
Right, according to you, one and one she wouldn't drink, even one
and one would stop the process. So in the end of the
משנה, Mishnah, when it's saying, you know, one and two stops the
process, when two says she became טמאה, tamei, why did you need
that? Could have said one and one stops the process and she
you assume that she's טמאה. tamei. So the end of the משנה
Mishnah is not coming to suggest that two and one this is
the way what be but one and one would be different. In
at least one of those cases, it wouldn't matter two and one
or one and one, whether you go רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya or
עולא. Ula. So that's not, don't overread that end of the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, so then why is the משנה Mishnah talking about two
and one? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא כולה
בפסולי עדות ורבי נחמיה היא. Ella kula be-pasulei edus ve-Rabbi Nechemya hi.
It's actually coming to tell you a different הלכה. halacha. Okay, whether
you say, you know, one and one neutralize, you know, or they
don't neutralize, what if we're not dealing with כשר kosher witnesses? What
if we're dealing with פסול pasul witnesses, with like case of a
woman, you know, who normally doesn't is isn't a כשר kosher witness.
Does she have the same weight?
And how does it factor in when there are multiple positions, you
know, you know, there are like multiple people saying different things. So
let's take a look. ורבי נחמיה היא. Ve-Rabbi Nechemya hi. It's going
like רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemya. דתניא De-tanya we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraisa, רבי נחמיה אומר כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הלך אחר
רוב דעות. Rabbi Nechemya omer kol makom she-hemina Torah ed echad halech
achar rov de'os. Whenever the תורה Torah believes one witness, because we're
operating not in the normal in the normal, you know, formal rules.
The normal formal rules is you need two and they have to
be כשר kosher witnesses. As soon as you're saying one, you've broken
all the rules, like there's no greater weight to a כשר kosher
witness or a פסול pasul witness. You've broken all the rules. And
if you've broken all the rules, then you could also go by
like a majority vote, okay? Normally, you know, two witnesses are equivalent
to a hundred witnesses when you're dealing with the formal rules of
testimony. But here, it doesn't have to be two, it can be
one, it doesn't have to be a כשר kosher witness, and therefore
you go by the greater number who is making the claim on
one side or the other. הלך אחר רוב דעות אפילו שתי נשים
באיש אחד כשני אנשים באיש אחד. Halech achar rov de'os afillu shtei
nashim be-ish echad kishnei anashim be-ish echad. Okay, and even and two
women, you know, against one man would be as good as two
men against one man. So, you know, you might be inclined to
say, well one man is a כשר kosher witness, two women aren't.
He says, no, no, no, this is playing by different rules, throw
your normal rules of testimony out the door, and two against one
wins even if the two are women and the one is a
man. So that's by the way a very powerful חידוש. chiddush. And
now we understand the end of the משנה. Mishnah. The end of
the משנה Mishnah is saying two against one win in both directions,
but it's telling you even if the one was a man and
the two were the women, you're going to go by the two
women, they're going to win. One against one, man and woman again,
men and women are all the same. So that would be whatever
normal one against one is, that's a debate of רבי חייא Rabbi
Chiyya and עולא. Ula. But the but that's not the point of
the end of the משנה. Mishnah. The point of the משנה Mishnah
is telling you that two women will beat out one man. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואיכא דאמרי כל היכא
דאתא עד אחד כשר מעיקרא אפילו מאה נשים נמי כעד אחד דמיין.
Ve-ika de-amrei kol heicha de-ata ed echad kosher me-ikara afilu me'ah nashim
nami ke-ed echad damyan.
So some don't want to take that position of רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemya that far. And want to say that if we're talking about
sequential, right? Because now that we said two beat out one about
according to רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, if two beat out one, that
doesn't have to be at the same
time. Right? Could be one and one, you know, that neutralize just
like עולא Ula said and excuse me one and one maybe we
go like עולא Ula and we always follow the one who says
טמאה. tamei. Okay,
but that is but that is one and one. If it's one
and two, we would always go by the two even if they
came later. So remember, both, you know, עולא Ula and רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiyya debate if they're coming at the same time, do you
do they get neutralized or not? But they all agree that if
somebody came later, if the first person said טמאה tamei and then
another person came later, you would not give weight to that later
testimony. That they all agree on, there's weight to the first one
and the first one has been accepted. This statement of רבי נחמיה
Rabbi Nechemya that you go by the majority could and it doesn't
matter כשר kosher or פסול, pasul, that could even sounds like it's
even if that they came later. So let's just appreciate that. Until
now everybody has agreed if the one that says did not become
טמאה tamei came later you ignore it. Comes רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya
and says no, it depends, if they're more in number, you would
believe those who came later, even if they were witness women testifying
against men a man, you believe those who came later if they're
more in number. So that's big חידוש chiddush number one. And that's
what the end of the משנה Mishnah is telling you. Now the
The גמרא Gemara says, you know what, maybe that's going a little
too far. Maybe if the first guy was a man, a כשר
kosher witness, then that would, and he came first, that would lock
it in, and even if you had 100, you know, women, that
would not neutralize this, this. A כשר kosher witness has greater weight
even in סוטה Sotah laws, even though it breaks the rules, one
is enough and we accept not כשר kosher witnesses, a כשר kosher
witness has special, special weight. So if the כשר kosher came first,
that's locked in, no testimony afterwards could do anything about it. Okay.
והכא במאי עסקינן כגון דאתי אשה מעיקרא. v'hacha b'mai askinan k'gon d'asi
isha me'ikara. Okay, but here our case where, you know, where, where
we are going, where the two neutralized the one, that the two
who said she did not become טמא tameh neutralized the one who
said טמא. tameh. So now if we're saying that it's one after
the other, how could two neutralize one if the one was the
man, he was locked in? How could the two that came later
neutralize? Oh, so because the one was a woman. If the one
was a woman, then that could be neutralized later by two women.
So what have we said now? Let's summarize. Okay. According to עולא,
Ula, everybody agrees that the one witness who says טמא tameh has
greater weight.
עולא Ula seems to say that even if at the same time,
we just listen to the one who says טמא. tameh. רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya says, no, no, no, if they came at the same
time, it's all in question. But if the one who says טמא
tameh comes first, that's when you would not listen to the one
who came later. Comes along רב נחמיה Rav Nechemia and he says,
there are time, no, actually, you will listen to people who come
later, even against the guy who said טמא, tameh, if they're more
in number. And here there are two versions. One is you'll always
listen to them, even women against men, and the other is you'll
listen to them if they're more in number, if it's like, you
know, women against a woman, or men against a woman, but a
woman against a woman. But when a man's testimony is first, then
that follows more normal rules of עדות, edus, and that's like two
normal כשר עדים, kosher eidim and nothing can overrule that. Okay, so
when it's a כשר עד, kosher ed, it becomes like two כשר
kosher עדים eidim, and nothing can overrule. When it's a woman, it
becomes like weighty evidence but not עדות, edus, and if there's more
people that come later, it would override. Okay. ותרצה לרבי נחמיה הכי.
v'tirtza l'Rabbi Nechemia hachi. And here's how to read רבי נחמיה. Rabbi
Nechemia. רבי נחמיה אומר כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הלך אחר
רוב דעות. Rabbi Nechemia omer kol makom she'he'emina Torah eid echad halach
achar rov deios. When the תורה Torah believes one witness, then we
go by the majority of the numbers.
ועשו שתי נשים באשה אחת כשני אנשים באיש אחד, v'asu shtei nashim
b'isha achas k'shnei anashim b'ish echad, which is two women against one
woman, the two would win out, the same way two men against
one man, the one would win out, and as we're saying, even
if they came later, they would win out. But that's when it's
all on the even playing field. אבל שתי נשים באיש אחד כפלגא
פלגא דמי, aval shtei nashim b'ish echad k'palga palga dami, but two
women against one man, the man said טמא tameh and that was
accepted, then because it's he's a כשר עד, kosher ed, that's like
real כשר עדות, kosher edus, and then the two women that come
against, they're, you know, it's like it's like equal, but it's not
like equal because the first testimony was accepted and they, you know,
coming later are not able to neutralize it. Okay. ותרי בפסולי עדות
למה לי. v'tarti b'psulei edus lama li. So why did the משנה
mishnah have to give both of those examples, you know, two coming
later and saying טמא tameh or two coming later and saying not
טמא? tameh? מהו דתימא כי אזלינן בתר רוב דעות לחומרא אבל לקולא
לא אזלינן קמשמע לן. ma d'teima ki azlinan basar rov deios l'chumra
aval l'kula lo azlinan k'mashma lan. I might have thought that you
go only by the majority when they come later to be lenient
but not to be strict, so it teaches you you will always
go by the majority number who come later, again assuming women and
women and men and men, according to this second read. What is
strict and what is lenient, whether it's strict to make her drink
or it's strict, or you know, you know, to allow her to
drink, or it's strict to not allow her to drink, so you
know, you could that sort of argue that both ways. רש״י Rashi
says that it's lenient that you say that you believe it's interesting
that you believe the witness and it's lenient that now she's not
able to drink. You know, you might think no, it's lenient that
you give her the option to drink. Okay, but anyway that's the
point. So fascinating about the weight of this one witness once he's
accepted according to עולא, Ula, maybe even if they come together, but
certainly once he's accepted it doesn't get overwritten after, this has special
weight. רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia says that if there are, that because
it's a, it's an exception, you normally don't believe one witness and
normally in כשר kosher witnesses you would actually you would override it
if there are a greater number afterwards. And then there's a question,
is that even true if the first person to testify was a
man? Because then that might be treated like real עדות edus and
which then could not be overridden afterwards. Okay, we will end here.